A Guide to the Pinkus family collection of Paul Ehrlich papers FA072
Rockefeller Archive Center
Pinkus family collection of Paul Ehrlich papers
1872-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ehrlich, Paul
Pinkus, Felix
Pinkus, Hermann
FA072
2.45 Cubic Feet 7 document cases
File Plan
Former Classification: I 650.2 eh89
Separated Materials
Books:
Ehrlich, Paul, Abhandlungen uber Salvarsan, Band I-IV, J. F. Lehmann, Munchen, 1911-1914
Mentberger, Victor, Entwicklung und gegenwartiger Stand der Arsentherepie der Syphilis, Gustav Fisher, Jene 1913.
Conditions Governing Access
To access the collection, written permission must be obtained from the Head of Donor Relations of the Rockefeller Archive Center, or an applicable designee.
Related Materials
FA135 Paul Ehrlich papers.
FA136 Paul Ehrlich and Martha Marquardt papers.
Biographical / Historical
Hermann Pinkus' father, Felix Pinkus was born April 4, 1868 in Berlin. In 1883 Felix's cousin Hedwing Pinkus was introduced to Paul Ehrlich in Felix's home, an event which led to the marriage of Hedwig to Paul Ehrlich in August 1883.
Felix Pinkus went on to study medicine in Berlin and Freiburg, later specializing in dermatolgy in Breslau under Albert Neisser. He returned to Berlin, becoming director of a woman's hospital and was made extraordinary professor (ausserordentlicher Professor) in 1921. In 1939 he immigrated to Norway and in 1941 to America where he lived with his son in Michigan until his death on November 19, 1947.
Because of his close relationship with Ehrlich and his cousin Hedwig, he attempted to write Ehrlich's biography, an endeavor which occupied his last years. The essay, "Studieren geht uber Probieren" however is the only complete manuscript. He tried to enlarge it and at the same time translate it into English. He also transcribed a few of Paul Ehrlich's copy books, which had been sent to him after their recovery in 1945.
After his father's death, Herman Pinkus tried to have the essay and the unfinished manuscript published, but without success. For the Ehrlich centennial in 1954 he wrote a few articles himself and made an Ehrlich exhibit at the American Academy of Dermatology and Syphilology in Chicago, for which he won first prize.
Scope and Contents
The Pinkus Family Collection, a special collection of the Rockefeller University, consists of correspondence to Felix and Hermann Pinkus. There are some original Paul Ehrlich letters, reprints of various authors, articles, paper clippings and obituary notes about Ehrlich. The many pages of Felix Pinkus' manuscipts remain unsorted. There are some photographs and material used for the 1954 exhibit in Chicago. The Collection covers the period 1872-1971.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement
As received.
Ehrlich, Paul; Pinkus, Felix; Pinkus, Hermann
- Hermann Pinkus correspondence
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Aron, Hans, 1952-1957; 36 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baeck. Leo Institute, 1971; 4 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    pamphlet of Institute, 2 lists of gifts
  - Carlisle, J.M., 1950; 2 reprints (Box 1, Folder 3)
    cortisone for Martha Marquardt
  - Chesney, Alan, 1952; 4 pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Pamphlets on Herter Lecture
  - Colliers Research Bureau, 1950-1951; 5 pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Curth, Helen, 1951; 2 reprints (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Du Shane, Graham, 1957; 2 obituaries (Box 1, Folder 7)
    obituaries on Shiga
  - Landau, Marianne, 1954-1955; 6 documents (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig, 1947-1948; 6 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ehrlich, Otto, 1952; 1 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Felsenfeld, Oscar, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Shiga obiturary and biography
  - Friedmann, Herbert, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    exhibit correspondence
  - Gans, Oscar, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Felix Pinkus Biography
  - Grab, Werner, 1954; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jokl, Ernst, 1954-1955; 9 items and one paper clipping (Box 1, Folder 14)
    exhibit in Kentucky; 1 paper clipping
  - Keyes, Preston, 1952; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Ehrlich visit in 1904
  - Lewey, Frederic, 1950; 4 documents (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Biography and copy books
  - Marquardt, Martha, 1950-1957; 15 documents (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Merker, Harvey, 1950; 1 document (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Michelson, Henry, 1969; 3 documents (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Felix Pinkus manuscript
  - New York University, 1952; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Herter Lecture
  - Novy, Frederick, 1950; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Prigge, Richard, 1955; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rothman, Stephen, 1954; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Separated Materials
    exhibit documents
  - Sanchez, Amado, 1954; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Information on Ehrlich
  - Scharenberg, Konstantin, 1955; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Biography
  - Schwerin, Hans, Gunther, 1950-1958; 20 documents (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Schwerin, Stefanie, 1948-1955; 7 documents (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Schwitalla, Alfonse, 1954; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 29)
    typscript copy of his talk
  - Sulzberger, Marion, 1948; 12 documents (Box 1, Folder 30)
    publication of Felix Pinkus manuscript and some related correspondence
  - Thompson, Lawrence, 1954; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 31)
    exhibit on Kentucky
  - Webster, James, 1954-1955; 4 documents (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Exhibit
  - Wile, U.J., 1955; 2 documents (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wright,Alan, 1950; 4 documents (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Cortisone for Martha Marquardt
  - Zakon, Samuel, 1954-1955; 10 documents (Box 1, Folder 35)
    exhibit and talk.
- Herman Pinkus article reprints, 1955; 2 reprints (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Correspondence H. Pinkus-O'Leary, re manuscript
  Reprints of "Paul Ehrlich and his impact on Dermatosyphilology", Archives of Dertmatology, August 1955
- Herman Pinkus typescript manuscripts, manscripts (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Herman Pinkus-typscript manuscripts "The Copy Books of Paul Ehrlich"
  Typscript manuscript, "In Commemoration of the 100 Anniversary of the Birth of Paul Ehrlich".
- Hans Aron typescript manuscript, 1 manuscript (Box 1, Folder 38)
  HansAron-Typescript manuscript "Paul Ehrlich, His Contributions to Medicine"
- Herman Pinkus exhibit material, exhibit material (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Herman Pinkus-Paul Ehrlich exhibit photographs and other related material.
- Herman Pinkus exhibit material-paper clippings, 1904; exhibit material (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Herman Pinkus-Paul Ehrlich exhibit, photocopies of newspaper clippings from 1904 and other exhibit material.
- Centennial in Frankfurt, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Centennial Celebration in Frankfurt 1954.
- Radio Show Transcript, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Transcript of BBC Radio Show: "Operation 606"
- Felix Pinkus correspondence
  - Albrecht, Adrien, 1947; 1 document (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Albrecht, Adrien correspondence
  - Elrlich, Hedwig, 1939-1941; 8 documents (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig, 1942; 8 documents (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig, 1943; 6 Documents (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig, 1944; 12 documents (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig, 1945; 7 documents and one newspaper clipping (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig, 1946; 2 documents (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Ehrlich, Hedwig, 1947; 5 documents (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Flexner, Abraham, 1942-1943; 2 documents (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gladston, Iago, 1944; 4 documents (Box 2, Folder 10)
    1 reprint
  - Ingersheim, Joseph, 1942-1943; 2 documents (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Marianne's eye infection.
  - Landau, Marianne, 1935-1946; 25 documents (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Mostly undated letters.
  - Lewey, Anna, 1944; 2 Documents (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Lewey, Frederic, 1943; 3 Documents (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Marquardt, Martha, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Michaelis, Leonor, 1916, 1942-1944; 12 documents (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Oppersdorf, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    one letter to Eisenhower
  - Pinkus, Eugen, 1941; 3 Documents (Box 2, Folder 18)
    3 postcards from Hewig to Felix's brother Eugen.
  - Schrag, Paul, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Schonberg, Dolly, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Schuching, Susanne, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Schwerin, Hans, 1942-1947; 4 documents (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Schwerin, Stefanie, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Takahashi, Akira, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Shiga Book
  - Weichbrodt, R., 1935-1939; 13 documents (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Hedwig and Joseph Pinkus letters, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Handwritten leeters to S. Frankel and 1 envelope.
- Paul Ehrlich letters to Hans Aron, 1908-1914; 4 documents (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Typewritten letters with original signature to Hans Aron.
- Paul Ehrlich letters to Arnold Berliner, 1899-1902; 9 Documents (Box 2, Folder 25)
  9 Handwritten letters to Arnold Berliner.
- Paul Ehrlich letters to Felix Pinkus, 1906-1915; 12 documents (Box 2, Folder 26)
  12 Letters to Felix Pinkus.
- Paul Ehrlich letters to Honor van der Velde, 1897; 3 documents (Box 2, Folder 27)
  3 Handwritten leeters to Honore van der Velde.
- Paul Ehrlich obituaries (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Paul Ehrlich Obituaries-Paper Clippings
- Genealogy (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Genealogy of families: Pinkus, Ehrlich and Frankel.
- Paper clippings, 1915-1940 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Paper clippings after 1940
- Salvarsan Reports, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Matters dealing with the evaluation of Salvarsan; paper clipping of a letter to the editor, condemning the choice of Ehrlich's professorship at the Frankfurt University.
- Articles about Paul Ehrlich before 1940 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Reprints of articles about Paul Ehrlich before 1940, including one by Felix Pinkus.
- Articles about Paul Ehrlich after 1940 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Various articles about Paul Ehrlich after 1940.
- Paul Ehrlich biographical material (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Various Biographical material about Ehrlich, including his letter to Herter (copy) and a letter by Albrecht Bethe.
- Photographs, 3 photographs (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Ehrlich's parents living room in Berlin and 2 photos of Heinamm Ehrlich.
- Hans Aronson Foundation By-laws (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Felix Pinkus manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 8, Folder 4, Folder 5, Folder 6, Folder 7, Folder 1, Folder 2, Folder 3)
  Various parts of German and English versions of Felix Pinkus' essay on Paul Ehrlich: "Studieren geht uber Probieren". Typed Manuscript in German pp. 1-117 (complete)
  Typed Manuscript, copy in German pp.1-27 (incomplete)
  Typed Manuscript of enlarged version, in English, pp. 1-128 (incomplete)
  Typed Manuscript of enlarged version, in English, pp. 1-53 (incomplete) but different version from version in Folder 3.
  Typed pages, about 100, addenda to German manuscript.
  Typed pages, about 40, addenda to English manuscript.
  Typed Manuscript of enlarged version in English, pp.1-28 with corrections by Felix Pinkus.
  Photocopy of manuscript in Folder 7.
- Felix Pinkus handwritten notes, 300 pages of handwritten and typewritten notes, no folders. (Box 4)
  Felix Pinkus handwritten and typewritten notes for a Paul Ehrlich biography, not sorted, approximately 300 pages.
- Felix Pinkus handwritten transcripts, 500 page copy book no folders. (Box 5)
  Felix Pinkus handwritten transcripts of a few Paul Ehrlich copy books, approximately 500 pages.
- Reprints by various authors, 1886-1980 (Box 6)
  Behring, Emil und Kitasato-"Uber das Zustandekommen der Diphtherie-Immunitat und der Tetanus-Immunitat bei Thieren" Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, No. 49, Berlin, 4, Dez, 1980.
  Berliner, Arnold-"Paul Ehrlich", Nachruf, Die Naturwissenschaften, No. 36, Springer, Berlin 3. September 1915.
  Ehrlich, Paul-"Uber die Sulfodiazobenzol Reaction", Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, No. 27, Berlin 1884.
  Studien uber die Cocainreihe", Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, No. 32, Berlin 1890.
  "Beitrage zur Theorie der Bacillenfarbung", Charite Annalen XI, Hirschwald, Berlin, 1886.
  "Histologie und Klinik des Blutes", Erster Theil, Hirschwald, Berlin, 1891.
  "Uber die Amfangsbehandlung der Lungen-und-Kehlkopf Tuberculose mit Koch'schem Tuberkulin", Deutsche Medizinische Wochemschrift, No. 10, Berlin, 1891.
  "Die Wirksamkeit Kleiner Tuberkulindosen gegen Lungenschwindsucht", Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, No. 24 Berlin, 1891.
  "Uber schwere Anamische Zustande", Verhandlungen des XI Congres fur innere Medicin zu Leipzig, 1892.
  "Uber die physiologische Wirkung der Verbindung der Cocainreihe", Berichte der Deutschen Chemischen Gesellschaft, XXVII, Heft 13, Berlin, 1894.
  "Uber die Gewinnung der Diphthereie-Antitoxine aus Blutserum und Milch immunisirter Theire" (with A. Wassermann), Zeitschrift fur Hygiene und Infectionskrankheiten, 18. Band. 1894.
  Ehrlich, Paul "Zur Kenntniss der Antitoxinwirkung", Fortschritte der Medicin, No. 2, Berlin 15 Jan. 1897.
  "Die Wertemessung des Diphitherieheilserums", Klinisches Jahrbuch, 6. Band, Fisher, Jena 1897.
  Minutes from a meeting of the Gesellschaft der Charite Arzte, 3. Feb. 1898 Berlin, Klinische Wochenschrift, No. 12, 1898.
  Uber die Constitution des Diphtheriegiftes", Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, No. 38. Berlin 1898.
  "Normale und Pathologische Histologie des Blutes", Specielle Pathologie und Therapie, Berlin, 1900.
  "Uber die Beziehung zwischen Toxin und Antitoxin", Gustav Fock, Leipzig, 1905.
  "Die Behandlung der Syphilis mit Salvarsan und verwandten Stoffen', Oxford Press, London, 1914.
  "Die Grundlagen der Chemotherapie", Handbuch der experimentellen Therapie, Serum und Chemotherapie, Lehman, Munchen, 1925.
  Gron, Kr. - "Paul Ehrlich" necrology, October, 1915.
  Kolle, W. - "Paul Ehrlich und Emil v. Behring", In Memoriam, 70th birthday, 1924, Franfurt.
  Kossel, H. - "Uber die Blutserumtherapie bei Diphtherie", Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, No. 43. Berlin 1894.
  "Weitere Beobachtumgen uber die Wirksamkeit des Behringschen Diphtherieheilserums", Deutsche Medizinische Wochenschrift, No.51. Berlin 1894.
  Lazarus, Adolf - "Beitrage zur Lehre von der Emigration des Hern Professor Dr. P. Ehrlich", poem written when Ehrlich moved to Frankfurt, 1899, ( in booklet labeled Jokl).
  Neisser, Albert - "Paul Ehrlich", necrology, Archiv fur Dermatologie und Syphilis Leipzig, 1915.
  "Einleitender Uberblick. Salvarsan und Syphilis", from Frstschrift, Gustav Fischer. Jena, 1914 (in booklet labeled Jokl).
  Petruschky, J. - "Zur Milchernahrung Tuberculoser", Deutsche Arzte Zeiting, No. 13, 1895.
  Pinkus, Felix - "Ehrlich als Therapeut", Medizinische Klinik, No.11, Berlin 1914.
  "Paul Erlich's Wirken", Medizinische Klinik, No. 40 u. 41, Berlin, 1915.
  Pinkus, Felix - "Paul Ehrlich", necrology, Medizinische Klinik, No. 35, 1915 (2) handwritten manuscript of this article, 2 pages.
  "Uber die Behandlung der Hirnschwellung nach Salvarsan", Dermatologische Zeitschrift, Band XXI, Heft 9, Berlin, undated.
  Sachs, Hans - "Paul Ehrlich und Emil v. Behring", In Memoriam, 70th birthday, 1924, Frankfurt.
  Schleich, Crl Ludwig - "Paul Ehrlich", necrology, George Muller, Munchen 1917.
  Schuching, Susanne V. - "Uber das Unverseifbara des Kaffee-bohnenols bzw. Des Kaffeewachses, insbesonderedere uber einen darin erhaltenen Oxyaldehyd", Inaugural Dissertation, Berlin, 1937.
  Vagedes, K. - "Uber Antitoxinausscheidung bei einem mit Tetanus serum behandelten Menschen", Zeitschrift fur Hygiene und Infectionskranheiten, 20. Band, Leipzig, 1895.
  Wassermann, August - "uber die personliche Disposition und die Prophylaxe gegenuber Diphtherie", Zeitschrift fur Hygiene und Infectionskrankheiten, 19, Band, 1895.
  Weinberg, Arthur v. - "Paul Ehrlich", necrology, Berichte der Deutschen Chemischen Gesellschaft, Band 49, Berlin, 1916.
- Reprints by Honore van der Velde, 1894-1912; 26 Reprints (Box 7, Folder 1, Folder 2, Folder 3, Folder 6, Folder 5, Folder 4, Folder 8, Folder 7)
  Reprints covering the period 1894-1912, 2 reprints undated. Mostly in French. explanatory note by Hermann Pinkus.
- Books, 1911-1914; 2 Books (Box 8)
  Ehrlich, Paul, Abhandlungen uber Salvarsan, Band I-IV., J.F. Lehmann, Munchen, 1911-1914.
  Mentberger, Victor, Entwicklung und gegenwartiger Stand der Arsentherapie der Syphilis, Gustav Fischer, Jena 1913.